<!-- -*- sgml -*- -->

<appendix id="svn.berkeleydb">
  <title>The Berkeley DB Legacy Filesystem</title>

  <para>Long ago, when Subversion first learned to store versioned
    data, it did so using a storage layer implementation based on the
    Berkeley DB (BDB) transactional database
    system.<footnote><para>Okay, strictly speaking, it used XML files
    for starters.  But that was never intended for public
    release.</para></footnote> As the product matured, though, this
    storage layer implementation was joined by&mdash;and then
    outmatched by&mdash;another one, the FSFS backend which is used by
    the vast majority of Subversion's repositories today.  In
    Subversion 1.8, the Subversion development community announced
    that the BDB-based storage layer was being officially
    deprecated.</para>

  <para>This appendix presents some of the documentation about
    administering BDB-backed repositories featured more prominently in
    previous versions of this book.</para>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.berkeleydb.configuration">
    <title>Configuring Your Berkeley DB Environment</title>

    <para>A Berkeley DB environment is an encapsulation of one or more
      databases, logfiles, region files, and configuration files.  The
      Berkeley DB environment has its own set of default configuration
      values for things such as the number of database locks allowed
      to be taken out at any given time, the maximum size of the
      journaling logfiles, and so on.  Subversion's filesystem logic
      additionally chooses default values for some of the Berkeley DB
      configuration options.  However, sometimes your particular
      repository, with its unique collection of data and access
      patterns, might require a different set of configuration option
      values.</para>

    <para>The producers of Berkeley DB understand that different
      applications and database environments have different
      requirements, so they have provided a mechanism for overriding
      at runtime many of the configuration values for the Berkeley DB
      environment.  BDB checks for the presence of a file named
      <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> in the environment directory
      (namely, the repository's <filename>db</filename> subdirectory),
      and parses the options found in that file.</para>

    <para>Subversion creates the <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> file
      when it creates the rest of the repository.  The file
      initially contains some default options, as well as pointers
      to the Berkeley DB online documentation so that you can read
      about what those options do.</para>

    <informalexample>
      <screen>
$ svnadmin create --fstype bdb /var/svn/repos
$ ls /var/svn/repos/db
changes        __db.003   __db.register  log.0000000001   revisions
checksum-reps  __db.004   format         miscellaneous    strings
copies         __db.005   fs-type        node-origins     transactions
__db.001       __db.006   locks          nodes            uuids
__db.002       DB_CONFIG  lock-tokens    representations
$
</screen>
    </informalexample>

    <para>Of course, you are free to add any of the supported Berkeley
      DB options to your <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> file.  Just be
      aware that while Subversion never attempts to read or interpret
      the contents of the file and makes no direct use of the option
      settings in it, you'll want to avoid any configuration changes
      that may cause Berkeley DB to behave in a fashion that is at
      odds with what Subversion might expect.  Also, changes made
      to <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> won't take effect until you
      recover the database environment (using
      <command>svnadmin recover</command>).</para>

  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.berkeleydb.limitations">
    <title>Limitations of Berkeley DB</title>

    <para>The Berkeley DB transactional data store offers all the data
      integrity promises that you'd expect from a world-class database
      system.  But every rose has its thorn, and so we must note some
      known limitations of Berkeley DB.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.limitations.architectural">
      <title>Architectural Limitations</title>

      <para>Berkeley DB environments are not portable.  You cannot
        simply copy a Subversion repository that was created on a Unix
        system onto a Windows system and expect it to work.  While much
        of the Berkeley DB database format is architecture-independent,
        other aspects of the environment are not.</para>

      <para>Second, Subversion requires the use of Berkeley DB in a
        way that will not operate on Windows 95/98 systems&mdash;if
        you need to house a BDB-backed repository on a Windows
        machine, stick with Windows 2000 or later.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.limitations.sharedfs">
      <title>Network Share Deployment</title>

      <para>While Berkeley DB promises to behave correctly on
        network shares that meet a particular set of
        specifications,<footnote><para>Berkeley DB requires that the
        underlying filesystem implement strict POSIX locking
        semantics, and more importantly, the ability to map files
        directly into process memory.</para></footnote> most
        networked filesystem types and appliances do
        <emphasis>not</emphasis> actually meet those requirements.
        And in no case can you allow a BDB-backed repository that
        resides on a network share to be accessed by multiple
        clients of that share at once (which quite often is the
        whole point of having the repository live on a network share
        in the first place).</para>

      <warning>
        <para>If you attempt to use Berkeley DB on a noncompliant
          remote filesystem, the results are unpredictable&mdash;you
          may see mysterious errors right away, or it may be months
          before you discover that your repository database is
          subtly corrupted.  You should strongly consider using the
          FSFS data store for repositories that need to live on a
          network share.</para>
      </warning>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.limitations.faulttolerance">
      <title>Fault Tolerance and the Need for Recovery</title>

      <para>Because Berkeley DB is a library linked directly into
        Subversion, it's more sensitive to interruptions than a
        typical relational database system.  Most SQL systems, for
        example, have a dedicated server process that mediates all
        access to tables.  If a program accessing the database crashes
        for some reason, the database daemon notices the lost
        connection and cleans up any mess left behind.  And because
        the database daemon is the only process accessing the tables,
        applications don't need to worry about permission
        conflicts.</para>

      <para>These things are not the case with Berkeley DB, however.
        Subversion (and programs using Subversion libraries) access
        the database tables directly, which means that a program crash
        can leave the database in a temporarily inconsistent,
        inaccessible state.  When this happens, an administrator needs
        to ask Berkeley DB to restore to a checkpoint, which is a bit
        of an annoyance.  Other things can cause a repository
        to <quote>wedge</quote> besides crashed processes, such as
        programs conflicting over ownership and permissions on the
        database files.</para>

      <note>
        <para>Berkeley DB 4.4 brings (to Subversion 1.4 and later)
          the ability for Subversion to automatically and
          transparently recover Berkeley DB environments in need of
          such recovery.  When a Subversion process attaches to a
          repository's Berkeley DB environment, it uses some process
          accounting mechanisms to detect any unclean disconnections
          by previous processes, performs any necessary recovery,
          and then continues on as though nothing happened.  This
          doesn't completely eliminate instances of repository
          wedging, but it does drastically reduce the amount of
          human interaction required to recover from them.</para>
      </note>

    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <!-- ================================================================= -->
  <sect1 id="svn.berkeleydb.maintenance">
    <title>Maintaining Berkeley DB Repositories</title>

    <para>In theory, the maintenance of a BDB-backed repository
      involves essentially the same steps used to maintain an
      FSFS-backed repository.  Historically, though, Berkeley DB
      repositories have need a little extra TLC<footnote><para>Tender
      loving care, Baby.</para></footnote> in order to stay
      operational.  This section will cover some of the unique aspects
      of Berkeley DB administration.</para>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.maintenance.recovery">
      <title>Berkeley DB Recovery</title>

      <para>As mentioned in
        <xref linkend="svn.berkeleydb.limitations.faulttolerance" />,
        a Berkeley DB repository can sometimes be left in a frozen
        state if not closed properly.  When this happens, an
        administrator needs to rewind the database back into a
        consistent state.  This is unique to BDB-backed repositories,
        though&mdash;if you are using FSFS-backed ones instead, this
        won't apply to you.  And for those of you using Subversion 1.4
        with Berkeley DB 4.4 or later, you should find that Subversion
        has become much more resilient in these types of situations.
        Still, wedged Berkeley DB repositories do occur, and an
        administrator needs to know how to safely deal with this
        circumstance.</para>

      <para>To protect the data in your repository, Berkeley
        DB uses a locking mechanism.  This mechanism ensures that
        portions of the database are not simultaneously modified by
        multiple database accessors, and that each process sees the
        data in the correct state when that data is being read from
        the database.  When a process needs to change something in the
        database, it first checks for the existence of a lock on the
        target data.  If the data is not locked, the process locks the
        data, makes the change it wants to make, and then unlocks the
        data.  Other processes are forced to wait until that lock is
        removed before they are permitted to continue accessing that
        section of the database.  (This has nothing to do with the
        locks that you, as a user, can apply to versioned files within
        the repository; we try to clear up the confusion caused by
        this terminology collision in the sidebar <xref
        linkend="svn.advanced.locking.meanings" />.)</para>

      <para>In the course of using your Subversion repository, fatal
        errors or interruptions can prevent a process from having the
        chance to remove the locks it has placed in the database.  The
        result is that the backend database system gets
        <quote>wedged.</quote>  When this happens, any attempts to
        access the repository hang indefinitely (since each new
        accessor is waiting for a lock to go away&mdash;which isn't
        going to happen).</para>

      <para>If this happens to your repository, don't panic.  The
        Berkeley DB filesystem takes advantage of database
        transactions, checkpoints, and prewrite journaling to ensure
        that only the most catastrophic of events<footnote><para>For
        example, hard drive + huge electromagnet =
        disaster.</para></footnote> can permanently destroy a database
        environment.  A sufficiently paranoid repository administrator
        will have made off-site backups of the repository data in some
        fashion, but don't head off to the tape backup storage closet
        just yet.</para>

      <para>Instead, use the following recipe to attempt to
        <quote>unwedge</quote> your repository:</para>
   
      <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Make sure no processes are accessing (or
            attempting to access) the repository.  For networked
            repositories, this also means shutting down the Apache HTTP
            Server or svnserve daemon.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem> 
          <para>Become the user who owns and manages the repository.
            This is important, as recovering a repository while
            running as the wrong user can tweak the permissions of the
            repository's files in such a way that your repository will
            still be inaccessible even after it is 
            <quote>unwedged.</quote></para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Run the <command>svnadmin recover</command> command:</para>
          <informalexample>
            <screen>
$ svnadmin recover /var/svn/repos
Repository lock acquired.
Please wait; recovering the repository may take some time...

Recovery completed.
The latest repos revision is 19.
$
</screen>
          </informalexample>
          <para>This command may take many minutes to complete.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Restart the server process.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
            
      <para>This procedure fixes almost every case of repository
        wedging.  Make sure that you run this command as the user that
        owns and manages the database, not just as
        <literal>root</literal>.  Part of the recovery process might
        involve re-creating from scratch various database files (shared
        memory regions, e.g.).  Recovering as
        <literal>root</literal> will create those files such that they
        are owned by <literal>root</literal>, which means that even
        after you restore connectivity to your repository, regular
        users will be unable to access it.</para>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.maintenance.bdblogs">
      <title>Purging unused Berkeley DB logfiles</title>

      <para>Prior to the release of Berkeley DB 4.2, the largest
        offender of disk space usage with respect to BDB-backed
        Subversion repositories were the logfiles in which Berkeley DB
        performs its prewrites before modifying the actual database
        files.  These files capture all the actions taken along the
        route of changing the database from one state to
        another&mdash;while the database files, at any given time,
        reflect a particular state, the logfiles contain all of the
        many changes along the way
        <emphasis>between</emphasis> states.  Thus, they can grow
        and accumulate quite rapidly.</para>

      <para>Fortunately, beginning with the 4.2 release of Berkeley
        DB, the database environment has the ability to remove its
        own unused logfiles automatically.  Any
        repositories created using <command>svnadmin</command>
        when compiled against Berkeley DB version 4.2 or later
        will be configured for this automatic logfile removal.  If
        you don't want this feature enabled, simply pass the
        <option>--bdb-log-keep</option> option to the
        <command>svnadmin create</command> command.  If you forget
        to do this or change your mind at a later time, simply edit
        the <filename>DB_CONFIG</filename> file found in your
        repository's <filename>db</filename> directory, comment out
        the line that contains the <literal>set_flags
        DB_LOG_AUTOREMOVE</literal> directive, and then run
        <command>svnadmin recover</command> on your repository to
        force the configuration changes to take effect.</para>

      <para>Without some sort of automatic logfile removal in
        place, logfiles will accumulate as you use your repository.
        This is actually somewhat of a feature of the database
        system&mdash;you should be able to recreate your entire
        database using nothing but the logfiles, so these files can
        be useful for catastrophic database recovery.  But
        typically, you'll want to archive the logfiles that are no
        longer in use by Berkeley DB, and then remove them from disk
        to conserve space.  Use the <command>svnadmin
        list-unused-dblogs</command> command to list the unused
        logfiles:</para>

      <informalexample>
        <screen>
$ svnadmin list-unused-dblogs /var/svn/repos
/var/svn/repos/log.0000000031
/var/svn/repos/log.0000000032
/var/svn/repos/log.0000000033
&hellip;
$ rm `svnadmin list-unused-dblogs /var/svn/repos`
## disk space reclaimed!
</screen>
      </informalexample>

      <warning>
        <para>BDB-backed repositories whose logfiles are used as
          part of a backup or disaster recovery plan should
          <emphasis>not</emphasis> make use of the logfile
          autoremoval feature.  Reconstruction of a repository's
          data from logfiles can only be accomplished only when
          <emphasis>all</emphasis> the logfiles are available.  If
          some of the logfiles are removed from disk before the
          backup system has a chance to copy them elsewhere, the
          incomplete set of backed-up logfiles is essentially
          useless.</para>
      </warning>

    </sect2>

    <!-- =============================================================== -->
    <sect2 id="svn.berkeleydb.maintenance.bdbutil">
      <title>Berkeley DB Utilities</title>

      <para>If you're using a Berkeley DB repository, all of
        your versioned filesystem's structure and data live in a set
        of database tables within the <filename>db/</filename>
        subdirectory of your repository.  This subdirectory is a
        regular Berkeley DB environment directory and can therefore
        be used in conjunction with any of the Berkeley database
        tools, typically provided as part of the Berkeley DB
        distribution.</para>

      <para>For day-to-day Subversion use, these tools are
        unnecessary.  Most of the functionality typically needed for
        Subversion repositories has been duplicated in the
        <command>svnadmin</command> tool.  For example,
        <command>svnadmin list-unused-dblogs</command> and
        <command>svnadmin list-dblogs</command> perform a
        subset of what is provided by the Berkeley
        <command>db_archive</command> utility, and <command>svnadmin
        recover</command> reflects the common use cases of the
        <command>db_recover</command> utility.</para>
            
      <para>However, there are still a few Berkeley DB utilities
        that you might find useful.  The <command>db_dump</command>
        and <command>db_load</command> programs write and read,
        respectively, a custom file format that describes the keys
        and values in a Berkeley DB database.  Since Berkeley
        databases are not portable across machine architectures,
        this format is a useful way to transfer those databases from
        machine to machine, irrespective of architecture or
        operating system.  As we describe later in this chapter, you
        can also use <command>svnadmin dump</command> and
        <command>svnadmin load</command> for similar purposes, but
        <command>db_dump</command> and <command>db_load</command>
        can do certain jobs just as well and much faster.  They can
        also be useful if the experienced Berkeley DB hacker needs
        to do in-place tweaking of the data in a BDB-backed
        repository for some reason, which is something Subversion's
        utilities won't allow.  Also, the <command>db_stat</command>
        utility can provide useful information about the status of
        your Berkeley DB environment, including detailed statistics
        about the locking and storage subsystems.</para>

      <para>For more information on the Berkeley DB tool chain,
        visit the documentation section of the Berkeley DB section
        of Oracle's web site, located at <ulink
        url="http://www.oracle.com/technology/documentation/berkeley-db/db/"
        />.</para>

    </sect2>

  </sect1>
</appendix>

<!--
local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("book.xml" "appendix")
end:
-->

